Guide to the Martin Bice Travis Papers
Stanford University Libraries
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Martin Bice Travis papers
1952-2006
SC0998
1.25 linear foot
Collection includes correspondence pertaining to the start of the Institute of American History and Government (Coe Program) at SUNY Stony Brook, 1964-65, and David Potter's participation in it, 1964-70; letters to Travis from James T. Watkins re Travis's position at Stanford, 1952-55; correspondence and some financial records re the selling of Travis's Stanford house (528 Alvarado), 1961-62; and obituaries of Travis and his wife Olivia, 2006.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Stanford University Libraries 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: speccollref@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://www-sul.stanford.edu/depts/spc/spc.html
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Helen Travis, 2010.
Biographical/Historical note
Educated at Amherst College and the University of Chicago, Travis taught briefly at Stanford before joining the faculty of SUNY Stony Brook where he helped establish the William Robertson Coe Institute of American Studies
Scope and Contents note
Collection includes correspondence pertaining to the start of the Institute of American History and Government (Coe Program) at SUNY Stony Brook, 1964-65, and David Potter's participation in it, 1964-70; letters to Travis from James T. Watkins re Travis's position at Stanford, 1952-55; correspondence and some financial records re the selling of Travis's Stanford house (528 Alvarado), 1961-62; obituaries of Travis and his wife Olivia, 2006; letters received from Prof. David Harris, Kristin Mullick [Glen], and Quincy Wright, 1962-1968; research notes and sources on the Panama Canal, 1959-1964; research proposal, notes, and correspondence re research on the Legal Adviser in the Department of State, 1967-61; Travis' lecture notes for a course, 1954, and term paper research note cards by students in the course.
Access Terms
Harris, David, (David W. Clancy), 1900-1975.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Potter, David Morris.; Watkins, James T. (James Thomas), 1907-1982.; Stanford University--Faculty housing.
Collection Contents
- Institute of American History and Government Summer 1965 (Coe Program), SUNY Stony Brook: correspondence, report, syllabi, bibliography, printed matter, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Potter, David: correspondence re Potter's participation in Coe Program at Stony Brook, 1964-1970 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Watkins, James T.: letters to Travis re his position at Stanford, 1952-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Watkins, James T.: obituary and note to Travis from Mrs. Watkins, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Buck, Philip W.: letters to Travis, clipping on book written by Buck and Travis, and undated letter on death of Buck, 1963, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Selling of Stanford house (528 Alvarado), 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Obituaries of Travis and his wife, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Travis' curriculum vitae, letter of recommendation from Graham H. Stuart, certificate of membership in the American Society of International Law (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Travis, clippings, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Letters received from Prof. David Harris, Kristin Mullick [Glen], and Quincy Wright, 1962-1968 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Committee on Research in Public Affairs (SU Dept. of Political Science)--project proposal re Legal Adviser in the Dept. of State and correspondence, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Committee on Research in Public Affairs (SU Dept. of Political Science)--research notes, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Committee on Research in Public Affairs (SU Dept. of Political Science)--research notes, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Panama Canal research, notes and sources, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Panama Canal research, sources, 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Panama Canal research, sources, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Panama Canal article by Travis and James Watkins in Foreign Affairs (1959): reviews and correspondence, including letters from Charles Fairman and Richard Nixon (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Panama Canal article by Travis and James Watkins in The Nation (1960 and 1964): letters from Daniel J. Flood, Col. Thomas Crystal Jr., and Ronald Hilton, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Articles by Travis, 1957-1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Travis' lecture notes for Poli Sci 131, 1954 (Box 3)
- Term paper research note cards by students in Poli Sci 131 (William Bosworth, Al Robertson, H. P. Brown, Herbert F. Steeper, Edmund P. Radwan, Tam Flower, and Robert R. Rezak) (Box 3)